{"tossups": [{"question": "Susan Reverby exposed one of these events that Francis Collins called a \u201cdark chapter in history;\u201dBarack Obama apologized for that event of this type to \u00b4Alvaro Colom, President of Guatemala. Eunice Rivers organized another of these events, whose victims included Herman Shaw and other men who were told they had \u201cbad blood.\u201d Either a placebo or penicillin was given to the infected subjects of, for ten points, what type of experiment that was conducted at Tuskegee University, in which African-American men were unknowingly given a sexually transmitted disease?", "answer": "<b> syphilis experiment</b>s (\u201dexperiment\u201d not needed after mentioned; prompt on partial answers; prompt on descriptions of experiments on humans (without informed consent), experimenting on humans (who don\u2019t know what\u2019s being done to them), etc.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The cut-stone Hall of Audience was commissioned by this ruler, who ascended to the throne after his predecessor disappeared on a voyage to explore the limits of the Atlantic Ocean. This ruler invited Ali Kolon to his court after conquering his homeland with the help of his general, Sagmandia. Andalusian architects were hired by this man to build the Djinguereber [jin-guh-rey-ber] Mosque in Timbuktu. For ten points, name this ruler of Mali who ruined economies with highly generous spending during his 1324 hajj to Mecca.", "answer": "Mansa<b> Musa</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This building was commissioned by William Reynolds after the Dreamland fire at Coney Island. A request from Texaco executives for an exclusive restaurant led to the creation of this building\u2019s Cloud Club. This building\u2019s exterior displays gargoyles and a recognizable terraced crown. Upon its completion in 1931, this William van Alen-designed building stood taller than the Empire State Building. For ten points, name this Manhattan skyscraper of the Art Deco style whose construction was funded by an American car manufacturer.", "answer": "<b> Chrysler</b> Building", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "This city\u2019s community of Lenasia is historically home to its Indian population, and its Carlton Centre is the tallest skyscraper on its continent. This city was established following the discovery of gold along the Witwatersrand. A formerly-separate suburb of this city is home to Orlando Stadium, which black students marched to in a 1976 protest against the mandatory teaching of Afrikaans. Soweto Township is now part of, for ten points, what city, the most populous in South Africa?", "answer": "<b> Johannesburg</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {"question": "In a quadrennial festival celebrating this deity, the<em> peplos</em> robe was setup like a ship\u2019s sail on a parade cart, while the<em> kanephoroi</em> carried sacred baskets alongside. One epithet of this deity, Glaukopis, refers to silvery eyes and was later translated as \u201cgray-eyed.\u201d Tetradrachm coins featured this goddess\u2019s face on one side and the owl, a prominent symbol of her wisdom, on the other. The Parthenon was dedicated to and named for, for ten points, what ancient Greek goddess, the virgin patron deity of Athens?", "answer": "<b> Athena</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "One depiction of this man shows him walking in front of mountains and clouds en route to a miners strike in Anyuan. He promoted socialist realism and artwork that was \u201cred, light and bright\u201d during his tenure. This man wears blue eyeshadow and rouge in a silkscreen print by Andy Warhol, and his official portrait by Ge Xiaoguang hangs on Tienanmen Gate. For ten points, name this leader who restricted artistic subjects through his Cultural Revolution policies as the first Chairman of Communist China.", "answer": "<b> Mao</b> Zedong (or Chairman<b> Mao</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "These people benefited from a form of welfare known as the<em> cura annonae</em>. These people forced the creation of the Twelve Tables and gained a measure of equality after the Conflict of the Orders. They often lived in the<em> subura</em> neighborhood in tenements known as<em> insulae</em>. Their elected representative could not be harmed, as he was considered sacrosanct, and could convene their namesake council as a tribune. For ten points, name these ordinary citizens of Rome, often at odds with the upper class patricians.", "answer": "<b> plebeian</b>s (or the<b> pleb</b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "To prevent complications in this process, the mTOR inhibitor rapamycin is used. Bruce Reitz and Thomas Starzl were innovators in this process, which Sir Roy Calne revolutionized by introducing ciclosporin, an immunosuppressant, to prevent rejection. Christiaan Barnard performed the first instance of this process involving the heart. For ten points, name this medical process in which another person\u2019s living tissue surgically replaces a damaged or missing system.", "answer": "organ<b> transplant</b> (accept descriptive answers; prompt on partial answers, like surgery)", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {}, {"question": "At an Iowa state fair, this man told a protester \u201ccorporations are people, my friend.\u201d In November 2016, Donald Trump was photographed having dinner with this former \u201cnever Trump\u201der, who was hoping to be Trump\u2019s pick for Secretary of State. Rick Perry called this man a \u201cvulture capitalist,\u201d attacking him for causing job losses while he led Bain Capital. A relatively popular health care reform bill was passed in 2006 while this man served as Governor of Massachusetts. For ten points, name this Republican politician, a Mormon who ran for President in 2012.", "answer": "Mitt<b> Romney</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "5 percent of the vote in Utah and the fifth-most popular votes overall.", "answer": "Evan<b> McMullin</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This group was legally given power by the<em> Lex Titia</em> and was formed after the Battle of Mutina. One of its members was forced out after raising a large force to defeat Sextus in Sicily. This group launched proscriptions against prominent politicians like Cicero. One member of this group divorced another\u2019s sister to ally himself with Cleopatra. For ten points, name this political alliance of the late Roman Republic that failed to stop a civil war between two of its members, Octavian and Mark Antony.", "answer": "<b> Second Triumvirate</b> (prompt on triumvirate)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "Lawson Knott oversaw the certification of this constitutional amendment. Birch Bayh and Emmanuel Celler co-named a proposal to pass this amendment, which had added stipulations missing from the earlier Keating-Kefauver proposal; those stipulations included a process that resulted in the ascent of Nelson Rockefeller to his highest post in 1974. For ten points, name this amendment that clarifies Vice Presidential confirmation and allows for the President to temporarily give power to the VP in cases of disability.", "answer": "<b> 25</b>th Amendment", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A novel by this author was probably inspired by the life of Enoch Crosby, a Revolutionary War era espionage agent whom he represented as Harvey Birch. A character created by this author, Judge Marmaduke Temple, gets rich by cheaply buying former Loyalist lands in the late 1700s. In a novel by this writer, Fort William Henry is surrendered to the French by Colonel Munro, whose daughter Cora is abducted by the Huron chief Magua. For ten points, name this author of<em> The Spy</em>,<em> The Pioneers</em>, and<em> The</em> <em>Last of the Mohicans</em>.", "answer": "James Fenimore<b> Cooper</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man helped end the Second Matabele [mat-ah-bay-lay] War by walking unarmed into an enemy base to negotiate; that base, Matobo Hills, later served as his burial grounds. This man\u2019s greatest dream was described as a \u201cred line\u201d on a map. Though this man never fulfilled his vision of a \u201cCape to Cairo\u201drailway, he managed to monopolize the diamond industry by founding De Beers. For ten points, name this Prime Minister of Cape Colony in South Africa, the namesake of a scholarship to study at Oxford.", "answer": "Cecil<b> Rhodes</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This empire secured power after defeating Marwan II at the river Zab. Chinese prisoners from the Battle of Talas aided this empire in establishing a paper mill at its capital, which</b> <b>had been moved from (+)</b> <b>Damascus by Al-Mansur. The mathematician Al-Khwarizmi</b> <b>worked in this empire\u2019s House of Wisdom, whose books allegedly turned the (*)</b> Tigris black from ink when Hulagu Khan sacked this caliphate\u2019s capital at Baghdad. Harun al-Rashid ruled over, for ten points, what caliphate that succeeded the Umayyad dynasty?", "answer": "<b> Abbasid</b> caliphate", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The ZLB problem refers to situations where this quantity approaches zero. The difference between two rates of this quantity is measured by the TED spread by using LIBOR, a</b> <b>version of this quantity that was (+)</b> <b>fraudulently manipulated in London, and this value</b> <b>for the U.S. Treasury bond. This quantity approaches zero in a liquidity trap, a situation that the U.S. has employed (*)</b> quantitative easing to try to avoid. In banking, an annual form of this quantity is described by the APR. For ten points, name this value which comes in simple and compound forms and represents the cost of borrowing money.", "answer": "<b> interest</b> rate", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Description acceptable. This transaction involved Jacob Ruppert giving three promissory notes for $25,000 each, plus another $25,000 up front, plus a loan for $300,000 secured by a mortgage on a property at 4 Yawkey Way. Harry Frazee made this deal to cover his financial</b> <b>losses on (+)</b> <b>musicals like</b><em><b> My Lady Friends</b></em><b>; four years later, Frazee\u2019s</b><em><b> No, No, Nanette</b></em> <b>was a smash hit. This transaction helped create the \u201cMurderer\u2019s Row\u201d of (*)</b> 1927 and led to an 86-year championship drought for the selling team. The \u201cCurse of the Bambino\u201d was triggered by, for ten points, what deal in which a legendary baseball slugger was sold by Boston to the Yankees?", "answer": "the<b> sale of</b> George Herman \u201cBabe\u201d<b> Ruth</b> from the Boston Red Sox to the New York Yankees (accept equivalents for sale, including<b> trade of Ruth</b> even though it was just player for cash)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b>This speech expressed the hope that the U.N. could be a \u201ctrue temple of peace\u201d and not merely a \u201ccockpit in a Tower of Babel.\u201d The speaker noted that \u201cthe United States stands</b> <b>at this time at the pinnacle of world power\u201d to an audience at (+)</b> <b>Westminster College,</b> <b>Missouri in 1946. Alternatively called the Sinews of Peace, this speech claimed that, \u201cfrom (*)</b> Stettin [...] to Trieste,\u201d the title construct had \u201cdescended across the continent.\u201d For ten points, name this speech by Winston Churchill that coined a term for the dividing line between Soviet and non-Soviet spheres.", "answer": "<b> Iron Curtain</b> speech (accept<b> Sinews of Peace</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This event proved difficult to stop once the Cornhill Tower was cut off. Attempts to mitigate this event were described by John Evelyn. Lord Mayor Thomas Bloodworth was (+) lambasted for his slow response to this event, which began at the bakery of Thomas Farriner on Pudding Lane, as described by the diary of Samuel Pepys [peeps]. St. Paul\u2019s (*)</b> Cathedral was destroyed in this event, so Christopher Wren was commissioned to redesign it and much of the city. For ten points, name this 1666 event that devastated England\u2019s capital.", "answer": "<b> Great Fire of London</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}